Joseph L. Zazyczny collection of American Council of Polish Culture records 1970-1989 CPAA 99-15
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Joseph L. Zazyczny collection of American Council for Polish Culture records
1970-1989
Joseph L. Zazyczny
CPAA 99-15
2 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Collection consists of records compiled by Joseph L. Zazyczny related to American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC). Mr. Joseph Zazyczny was the ACPC president from 1987-1989. The bulk of the material covers the years 1984-1989. It includes also materials from annual state conventions, extensive correspondence and documentation of the Washington project, which was a major undertaking of the council in 1980's that went well into 1990's. The main goal of the Washington project was to establish ACPC presence in Washington to promote Polish culture on the national and international level. The collection also includes also information about affiliated members and their activities.
Historical/Biographical Note
The American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC) was established in 1948 under the name American Council for Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC) to represent on a national level the interest of many Polish American cultural organizations that already existed in the United States. The oldest cultural organization, the Polish Arts Club of Chicago, was established in 1928. Currently the ACPC has about 250 members and accepts individual and organizational members. The main mission of the organization is to support a network of organizations to promote Polish language, art, history, and cultural involvement and awareness. The name change from The American Council for Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC) to The American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC) was proposed in 1987 and become official in 1988 and still is the official name. And yet another name change occured, however short, during Blanka Rosenstiel presidency(1984-1986)to the American Council of Polish Cultural Organization (ACPCO)to reflect the change in mission of the organization. However it did not receive acceptance from all members. The name American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC) is an official name of the organization. All three versions of the name are in use in various folders description but it is still the same organization.
Joseph L. Zazyczny was born in 1935 in Philadelphia, the son of John and Mary Zazyczny. He attended Catholic elementary and secondary schools in the city and later attended Alliance College, the University of Colorado, and Temple University. In 1967, Joseph Zazyczny was elected to the Philadelphia City Council. His district was made up of a large number of Polish American citizens. Mr. Zazyczny was both Founder and President of the Polish Heritage Society of Philadelphia, a group dedicated to promoting Polish culture through art, language, and music programs. He also served as President of the Polish Intercollegiate Club, an organization of local Polish American college graduates that encouraged local Poles to pursue their higher education. Mr. Zazyczny helped to foster achievement and recognition of many Polonia organizations. He was member of American Center of Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC), and first become one of its national directors and in 1987 was elected its President.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
American Council for Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC) was founded 1948 ACPCC changed its name to American Council for Polish Culture in late '80s. Jozef Zazyczny was one of national directors and in 1986 become president of the organization. The collection consists of records related to ACPC activities from 1970 till 1989, however the bulk of the material covers years 1984-1989 during intense involvement of Mr. Zazyczny. Material from the conventions includes official publications, related correspondence, various reports, press clippings and information on convention preparation activities. Material related to the Washington projects illustrates the initial discussions, establishing committee and extensive fundraising efforts for the project, and related correspondence. Remaining material in the collection relates to ACPC involvement with establishing scholarships, organizing concerts and lectures as well as gaining new members and attracting young members for the organization.
The collection is open for research.
Donated by Mr. Joseph Zazyczny in 1990.
Search Terms
Zazyczny, Joseph L.; American Council for Polish Culture -- History.; Polish Americans -- Societies, etc.; American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs -- History.; Conventions.; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
American Council for Polish Culture records CPAA 96-03
Alfred F. Bochenek collection of American Council for Polish Culture records CPAA 02-01
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged in five series and foldres witin each series are in chronological order:
Series I ACPC Conventions 1970-1989
Series II ACPC Washington project 1986-1989
Series III ACPC General activities 1977-1989
Series IV ACPC General correspondence 1984-1988
Series V ACPC Members and affiliates, 1981-1989
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Series I: American Center for Polish Culture Conventions, 1970-1989
  - ACPCC - 22nd Annual Convention, souvenir booklet, Alliance College., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ACPCC - 25th Convention, minutes, souvenir pamphlet, Villanova University, PA, August 13-19, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - ACPCC - 25th Convention, souvenir booklet, related correspondence, Villanova, PA., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ACPCC - 25th convention, program, financial information, correspondence., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ACPCC - 31st Annual Convention, minutes, Milwaukee, WI., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACPCC - Annual report for Convention., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ACPCC - 32nd Annual Convention, minutes, San Antonio., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ACPCC - 33rd Annual Convention, St. Louis, MO., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ACPCC - 34th Annual Convention, minutes, Chicago, IL., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ACPCC - 35th Annual Convention, souvenir booklet, minutes and annual report, Baltimore, MD., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ACPCC - 36th National Convention, souvenir booklet, annual report, Washington D.C., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ACPCC - 37th National Convention, program, minutes and related correspondence, Buffalo, NY., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ACPCC - 37th National Convention, souvenir booklet, Buffalo, NY., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ACPCC - 38th National Convention, Souvenir booklet, report, agenda, Cambridge Springs, PA., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ACPCC - 39th National Convention, souvenir booklet, business agenda, speech of Carl J. Merling, Ypsilanti, MI., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ACPCC - 39th National Convention, minutes, reports, flyers, correspondence, Ypsilanti, MI., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ACPCC - 40th National Convention, Hartford, CT., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ACPCC - resolutions adapted at 39th and 40th annual conventions., 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ACPCC - 41st National Convention, Philadelphia, PA., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ACPCC - convention guidelines and related correspondence., 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: ACPC Washington project, 1986-1989
  - ACPCC - Washington project, sales of premises in Stamford to benefit the project., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ACPCC - Washington project, raising money, pledge program., 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ACPCC raffle ticket list for Washington project., October 10, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ACPCC - Washington project, list of donors., between 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ACPCC - Washington Project, correspondence and reports., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ACPCC - Washington project, correspondence and reports, fund raising efforts, clippings., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Proposed guidelines for the American Center of Polish Culture in Washington, D.C., March 19, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - ACPCC - Washington project - chairperson report by Blanka Rosenstiel., August 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - ACPC - Washington project, donors list of $100 and more., March 1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - ACPC - Washington Project, correspondence, reports, and donations., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - ACPC - Washington project, correspondence and reports., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - ACPC - Washington project, account information., 1987-1988x (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The American Center of Polish Culture, Inc. - Articles of Incorporation., November 28, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series III: ACPC General information and activities, 1977-1989
  - ACPC - constitution, by-laws, drafts and final version., 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ACPCC - correspondence related to ACPCC archives., 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ACPCC - Message from the President - Joseph Zazyczny., 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - ACPCC - Message from the President - Stanley Ciesielski., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ACPCC Reports of the Treasurer., 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - ACPCC - Board of Directors meeting, minutes, agendas, related correspondence., 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ACPCC - ACPCO A Program for Now, by Blanka A. Rosenstiel and related correspondence., 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - ACPCC - Awards committee, list of recipients, official rules, correspondence., 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - ACPCC - Joseph Pabis Memorial Scholarship., 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - ACPCC - Marcelina Sembrich Award Concert and biographical information., 1986 and 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - ACPCC - Cyprian Norwid Memorial Committee, correspondence., 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - ACPCC - lecture series and public programming on Polish and Polish American topics, includes correspondence, reports and grant initiatives., 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ACPCC - Trilogy panel report - Kuniczak translation, related correspondence, finances., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - ACPCC - flyers, advertisements, notes related to promoting of Polish history and culture in the US., 1970's-1980's (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Polish American Catholic and His Piety, A Selected Bibliography, State University of New York, Buffalo, by Manuel D. Lopez., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series IV: ACPC General correspondence, 1984-1988
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - ACPC - correspondence., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - ACPC - correspondence with Thaddeusz Maliszewski and letters to editors related to anti-defamation., 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series V: ACPC Members and affiliates, 1981-1989
  - ACPC - membership and affiliates information., 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - ACPC - Organization and Public Relations Manual for ACPCo Affiliates., [1984] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - ACPC - membership list., 1986,1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - ACPC - list of clubs correspondence related to membership., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - ACPC - membership committee, correspondence, reports, lists of members., 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - ACPC and Young Americans of Polish Descent controversy and related correspondence., 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - ACPC - Young Americans of Polish Descent, 2nd Annual conference, and directory., August 19-23, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - ACPC - Polish Arts Club of Chicago directory., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - ACPCC - directory., 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)